Guide to the Frank Gould Papers 1930-1993 MS 3228
New-York Historical Society
Frank Gould papers
1930-1993
1940-1950
New-York Historical Society
Gould, Frank R., 1906-1993
MS 3228
2.25 Linear feet
3.73 Gigabytes 337 Files, 1 Folder
The Frank Gould papers comprise letters, scripts, and ephemera related to Frank Gould's life and career as a writer in New York City for radio dramas, Broadway, magazines, and newspapers. The bulk of this collection focuses on the 1940s and his writing, including scripts he wrote for Inner Sanctum Mystery, a radio program that aired from 1941 to 1952. In addition, there is a scrapbook made by Gould and a digital copy of his autobiography, God Shed His Grace on Me, written shortly before his death in 1993.
Arrangement
This collection is organized by topic and genre. Folders are arranged chronologically when possible.
Biographical / Historical
Frank Gould (born Frank Raful Goldberg), a Jewish New Yorker born in 1906, was a prolific playwright and actor throughout his life. This collection, the bulk of which dates from the 1940s, features many of the scripts he wrote for Broadway shows and radio dramas. It also documents his time in the U.S. Office of War Information Features Division as a writer in the 1940s. Born in Brooklyn, Gould went to Columbia University for college and graduated from the School of Journalism. Soon after, he spent time on the staff of the Brooklyn Eagle, a daily newspaper published from 1841 to 1955, and the Brooklyn Times-Union, itself bought by Brooklyn Eagle in 1937, before focusing on his playwriting and acting. Around this time, he also met and married Ruth Yogendorf Gould on May 30, 1936.
Working freelance for Himan Brown, an American producer of over 30,000 radio programs, Gould wrote scripts for radio programs such as March of Time, one of the first dramatized radio newsreels -- staged and performed like a drama while sharing news content. Gould also wrote for The Columbia Workshop, a program dedicated to entertaining and experimenting with the genre of radio drama. In 1941, he created the program City Desk, a radio drama that followed two detectives as they uncovered murder mysteries, exposed corrupt politics, and pursued romance in the large metropolis. Although uncredited, Gould also wrote the first, seventh, and tenth episodes of Inner Sanctum Mystery, a popular radio program mixing horror and humor that aired from 1941 to 1952 (the scripts can be found in the collection). At the same time, Gould performed on Broadway in such productions as Having Wonderful Time (1937-1938), Escape This Night (1938), and Cafe Crown (1942) and wrote plays such as The Scene of the Crime (1940). Before World War II Gould also worked as a social director for a venue in the Catskills, part of the "Borscht Belt."
Following the entry of the United States into World War II, Gould became a member of the Features Division in the Office of War Information for the U.S. Army in the North African Theater. He was deployed in 1943 as a non combatant in the Middle East and spent time in Palestine, Turkey, and Egypt, among other countries. Throughout his time in the army, he created reports on various war fronts and countries and wrote plays about the war, such as Homage to Bataan. He also originated, wrote, and voiced the "Chaplain Jim" radio broadcast during World War II.
After World War II, Gould returned to writing, notably creating the Broadway show Tenting Tonight in 1947 (also referred to as Snow-Job in the collection), which was picked up by a number of theaters. At the same time, he began to write for magazines such as Reader's Digest, True Experiences, and True Romance, assuming editorial reponsibility for both True Experiences and True Romance. He also instructed aspiring playwrights at conferences around the country.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to all qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Nancy Gould Thompson and Rita Gould Maidat Sohni, daughters of Frank Gould, April 4, 2023.
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society Museum holds Gould's World War II blanket and knapsack.
Two of Gould's plays, The Scene of the Crime and Snow-Job, are housed in the Performing Arts Research Collection -- Theatre of the New York Public Library. Their call numbers are NCOF+ (Gould, F. Scene of the Crime) and RM 184, respectively.
Scope and Contents
Consisting of three boxes, this collection features complete original scripts, contracts, professional and personal correspondence, reviews of plays and radio dramas, short stories, newspaper and magazine articles, photographs, and military documents as well as a scrapbook made by Gould and a digital copy of his autobiography. The bulk of the materials document Gould's professional career on Broadway and in radio dramas as well as his subsequent work as a magazine editor for publications such as True Experiences.
Playwriting -- New York (State) -- New York; Radio scripts; Theater -- New York (State) -- New York.; Theater -- Reviews; United States -- Armed Forces -- Civilian employees; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda.; Abbott, Judith, 1922-1984; Bulldog Drummond (Radio Program); Columbia Artists Management, Inc.; Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc.; Columbia Workshop (1936-1943); Fulton Theatre (New York, N.Y.); Inner Sanctum (Radio Program); March of Time (Radio Program); Mason, Mary, 1911-1980; New York Times Company; Radio Stars Magazine (1932-1938); Reader's Digest Association; True Experience (1922-1980s); United States. Office of War Information; Variety Magazine; WABC (New York, N.Y.); Waring, Fred, 1900-1984; Writer's Digest Books
- Military Service Papers, 1943-1945
  Scope and Contents
  The material in this box documents some of the work Frank Gould did for the Office of War Information during World War II as a part of the Features Division in the Office of War Information. The documents, which include personal correspondence with Gould's wife (Ruth Yogendorf Gould), photographs, a script produced for the Office of War Information, and various documents from his time as a noncombatant employee, detail Gould's time in North Africa from 1943 to 1945.
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
    3 letters to Ruth Yogendorf Gould, wife of Frank Gould, during his deployment.
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Photos from Gould's time abroad during World War II as well as a large-scale portrait of Frank Gould from later in his life.
  - Play Script for the Office of War Information (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Homage to Bataan, written by Frank Gould for the Office of War Information.
  - U.S. Army Administrative Documents and Papers (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Documents related to Frank Gould's deployment, including identification cards and press badges.
  - U.S. Army Language Manuals (Box 1, Folder 5)
    German Phrase Book (1), Japanese Phrase Book (1), Italian Phrase Book (1).
  - U.S. Army Paraphernalia (Box 1)
    Pair of U.S. Army cufflinks and rank insignia.
- Playwriting and Related Materials, 1935-1970
  This box contains much of Gould's professional career, including original scripts for radio dramas and stage plays, contracts and letters from agents, and magazines for which he wrote or edited. The material ranges from 1935 to 1970.
  - Magazines and Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Professional Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Radio Scripts, 1935-1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Radio Scripts, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Tenting Tonight Licensing and Contractual Materials (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Theater and Stage Scripts (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Writing Conference Bulletins (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Scrapbook, 1930-1957 (Box 3)
  Created by Frank Gould, the scrapbook contains collages of reviews from Gould's shows, programs and tickets, pictures of Gould acting for radio dramas, and other documents. There are also some professional documents relating to Gould's projects.
- Autobiography: God Shed His Grace on Me, 1993 (Digital-folder 1)